<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A door opened to the imprisoned seed in the vvorld, and the way of freedom by the spirit of truth, sent out into the world in love to the sheep that have long been lost, which may serve any who simply seek the life of what they possess, and may shew the feigned &amp; false in heart, the cause why they are shut out of truths power : wherein the elect way is opened to the blind, with encouragements to enter and walk therein : also the fruits of the free-born cleared from legal performances, and the children of bondage shewed the nature of their own works : Christ Jesus known to be king in his temples, through the power of the Holy Ghost, and sword of the spirit lifted up against the man of sin in true judgment / by J.N.</title>
            <author>Naylor, James, 1617?-1660.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1667</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 114 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 24 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A52687</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing N277</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R23128</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12493139</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12493139</idno>
            <idno type="VID">62428</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A52687)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 62428)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 769:30)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A door opened to the imprisoned seed in the vvorld, and the way of freedom by the spirit of truth, sent out into the world in love to the sheep that have long been lost, which may serve any who simply seek the life of what they possess, and may shew the feigned &amp; false in heart, the cause why they are shut out of truths power : wherein the elect way is opened to the blind, with encouragements to enter and walk therein : also the fruits of the free-born cleared from legal performances, and the children of bondage shewed the nature of their own works : Christ Jesus known to be king in his temples, through the power of the Holy Ghost, and sword of the spirit lifted up against the man of sin in true judgment / by J.N.</title>
                  <author>Naylor, James, 1617?-1660.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <editionStmt>
                  <edition>The second edition, corrected.</edition>
               </editionStmt>
               <extent>47 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1667.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Society of Friends --  Doctrines.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:62428:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:62428:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A Door Opened TO THE Impriſoned Seed IN THE VVORLD: And the way of Freedom, by the Spirit of Truth, ſent out into the World in love to the Sheep that have long been loſt.</p>
            <p>Which may ſerve any who ſimply ſeek the life of what they profeſs; and may ſhew the feigned &amp; falſe in heart, the cauſe why they are ſhut out of Truths Power.</p>
            <p>Wherein the Elect way is opened to the blind, with encouragements to enter and walk therein.</p>
            <p>Alſo the Fruits of the Free-born cleared from legal performances, and the Children of Bondage ſhewed the nature of their own works.</p>
            <p>Chriſt Jeſus known to be King in his Temples, through the Power of the Holy Ghoſt, and Sword of the Spirit lifted up againſt the Man of Sin in true Judgement.</p>
            <p>By <hi>J. N.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Second Edition, corrected.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>If you know the Truth, it ſhall make you free.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed in the Year, 1667.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:62428:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:62428:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>A Door opened to the Impriſoned Seed in the World, and the way of freedom by the Spirit of Truth, ſent into the World in love to the Sheep that have long been loſt.</head>
            <p>EVery Creature being born of corrupted nature, hath that ſpirit in him that luſts enviouſly againſt God, and that ſeed in him, and growing up with him, which daily ſeeks to enſnare his Soul further into wickedneſs and vanity, and to increaſe his ſeparation from God, by drawing in iniquity, and filling the Temple where God ſhould dwell and be known, with the accurſed things which God hates and cannot behold; for this evil ſeed being ſubtile and forward, prevails above the pure Life, and leads out the mind from it into many ſeveral temptations, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting them with delight unto the carnal part, and outward ſences, whereby the Seed of God becomes continually vailed and hid from the creature, ſo that man knows not that Word of Life by which he was created, nor can he come to be guided by it in himſelf, till the head of this evil ſeed be bruiſed, through believing in that Light which comes from the Life, by which the World was made; and this is that Rock which follows man with its unchangeable te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony, bearing witneſs onely to that which is of himſelf, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all the wayes of that evil ſeed, calling and reproving the World becauſe thereof, which call as many as receives and hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kens to, by Faith comes to hear the Word of Life, wherein Power is received to become the Sons of God; which Power of Life, as it ariſes in the Promiſed Seed, the head of the evil ſeed is bruiſed, and he comes to be brought under, who had taken the Soul captive at his will to every vain and evil work: and ſo as the Creature comes to be redeemed from under the power of darkneſs, ſo he comes to be guided in the Light of that Life by which he came into the World; and that Light which before reproved him for his deeds of darkneſs (following him from one to another, condemning him
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:62428:3"/>
in all, being turned to by Faith and Obedience) now becomes his Leader out of the World, to the Son of God, in whom Gods Righteouſneſs is revealed from above<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> to juſtification; which Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs being received into, and abiding in, ſin is remembred no more: and thus man being changed into that Nature which changeth not in the inward man, comes to love that Light which before he could not, for no man can love that which is of God, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til he hath received Gods love.</p>
            <p>Now the Light of the World, is Gods love to the World; for God ſo loved the World when it was in the power of darkneſs, that he gave his Son into the World, a Covenant of Light, that whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever followeth him ſhould not abide in darkneſs, but ſhould have the Light of Life; Now Gods Love <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> in the light of the World, That's his Covenant with the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>d, which whoſoever rejects and receives not, is out of Gods love, and in the enmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, out of Gods Covenant, neither can he in that ſtate believe that Gods love is in it. And this is the cauſe why all men ſpeak evil of the Light, who love their evil deeds, and cannot receive it as Gods Love, and the way to life, to ſuch it is condemnation; not that it was intended thereto; but men loving darkneſs rather then light, it becomes condemnation; but to him that believes, and is obedient, to him it is precious: for who follows it out of the World, there receives the Nature of Sons, and the Love of the Father, which the World cannot receive, and the Power of God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs, and Treaſure of eternal Life; and this is not given to any till they come out of the World, as he is not of the World, for therein ſtands Gods Covenant with <hi>Abrahams</hi> Seed for ever.</p>
            <p>So Gods Love to the World (while men are in that corrupt na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and the Witneſs of the Spirit of Truth) is to reprove the World of ſin, and teſtifie condemnation againſt the deeds thereof; but to ſuch as have received it, it's a Leader, Comforter, and Saviour; and this is the cauſe why the one loves, and the other hates, each Nature ſpeaking that ſtate in which it ſtands towards God, and as it hath obtained from him in Chriſt Jeſus, love or condemnation; and he that will not receive Gods love that calls him out, muſt abide under the power of the ſeed which God hates; and this is he that ſeeks to murther him that is in Gods love, the evil one having power to blind that mind (who denies the Light)
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:62428:3"/>
ſo far, till he cannot ſee that the Murtherer is of the Divel, but thinks he is doing God ſervice; and this in the end hath ever be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallen ſuch Profeſſors as reject the Light of the World, for he that walks in darkneſs knows not whither he goes; but God is Light, and in him is no darkneſs at all, nor hath darkneſs any fellowſhip with him: here is known the Children of God, and the children of darkneſs; he that loves the Light, brings his deeds to the Light, and hath fellowſhip with God in his deeds, and this works the Work of God; and he that denies the Light, works in darkneſs, and cannot believe the Power that is in the Light, being under the power of darkneſs.</p>
            <p>And therefore he that is born after the fleſh, knows not him that is born after the Spirit of Light, nor can judge of his wayes, which are ſtrange and wonders in his carnal ſight, neither knows he by what power and love that is, by which he overcomes the World, and takes pleaſure in denying the pleaſures thereof, and vanquiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth all its vanities out of the heart and mind, and can no more re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce in the World, nor make merry with its mirth; but rejoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth in the Truth, and is made glad with that which ſaves him from ſuch folly; the wicked knows not the life of the Righteous, nor the ſpring whence his Virtues ariſe, nor the power of his Change, nor the end of all his patient ſufferings and tryals, but ſtands won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering at it as folly and madneſs; that eye being blinded by the god of this world, which ſhould give the ſight thereof, and that ſeed in bondage under the prince of darkneſs, which ſhould give to inherit that immortal Treaſure; and this muſt be, till there be a denying and coming out of the World to receive that inheritance of divine Light and underſtanding, which none can receive, nor be one withal, but as they come out of the world from under that ſeed of enmity which ſeeks to pervert all the right wayes of God, and wreſt all his gifts to mans deſtruction as far as he can pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail.</p>
            <p>Now this deſtroyer or ſeed of enmity againſt the Life of man, and his Salvation, is kept from that ſudden effecting his purpoſe upon the creature in whom he is head, by no other thing, but the patience and long-ſufferings of God, who willing that none of his Creatures ſhould periſh, but that if by any means all might hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken to the Truth, and ſo recover themſelves out of the ſnares of
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:62428:4"/>
this ſubtile deceiver and be ſaved; wherefore he doth many times long bear and forbear with much patience, and diligence, ſtriving by the Spirit of Truth, upon all occaſions, when ever the Creature doth but mind it, checking, and reproving, and warning, even many times, at that very inſtant when the act of ſin is committing; and if the evil one have got ſuch power in the creature, that he will not ſuffer him to mind reproof before, nor in the act of ſin, then afterwards when the heat of temptation is cooled, then he ſhews the evil and danger of ſuch wickedneſs, that ſo he might preſerve fear in him againſt the next temptation. And thus (in many) he keeps back deſtruction a long time, ſo that ſome are long ere the wicked one get them to fill up their meaſure; and ſome in that time of Gods patient forbearing and ſuffering, come to repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, and turn to that which reproves, and are ſaved; and others go on to deſtruction, which ſwiftly they draw upon themſelves af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter once the Spirit hath ceaſed ſtriving and reproving; for then the fear is loſt, and the evil one hath his liberty at his own will, (the Creature being given up of the Lord, and the Spirit of Truth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing wholly departed) nought but deceit is left to guide him who hath dealt deceitfully with the Spirit of Truth, which at the beſt hath but a form of godlineſs without the Power; for the Power of God is in that Spirit, and in that Life which is known, by with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the evil one, which is fallen and covered in ſuch, in whom death reigns; only ſuch who are born of the Spirit, have the Life and Power, and know its ſtrength and virtue unto eternal Salvation; the reſt are left to their thoughts and notions.</p>
            <p>And here is the cauſe of that ſtrong contention that hath ever been betwixt the Children of Light, who are born of that Spirit of Truth, and have their light and ſtrength in the inward man; and the worlds profeſſors, whoſe expectation ſtands in ſomething with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out them, which others have ſpoken of who had it in them; and ſo not knowing the Power and Myſtery of the living Faith, which is holden in a pure Conſcience, which only hath the Call and Power to bring out of the worlds darkneſs, they are kept captive therein, contending againſt the Spiritual Light; and ſo while they are in the world, go about to comprehend and meaſure that Spirit of Truth, which the world cannot receive, neither knoweth, think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that Spirit of <hi>Light</hi> and <hi>Life</hi> to have no other op<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>ion in ſuch
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:62428:4"/>
who are led out of the world, and born thereof, and in whom Chriſt lives, than they find it to have in themſelves, who ſtumble at it, and are diſobedient and unbelieving in heart; when as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed to us that believe, it is Elect and Precious who come to it for all ſupplies; but to the wiſdom and profeſſion of the world, it is a Rock of offence, and ſtumbling-ſtone, yet is it the Head of the Corner; and in them who revile it and reject it, it is become all they have in them that is good, true, and faithful towards God, or their Souls, as their hearts in ſecret do witneſs to them, and leaves them without excuſe many times.</p>
            <p>For even they that reject this Light and Spirit, have nothing elſe that can ſhew them ſo much as one of their thoughts, or divide to their underſtanding the evil from the good, either in Thought, Word, or Action, or that can really ſhew them what is of God really, and what is of him, who doth but ſhew himſelf to be God to deceive withal, and is not; nor without it can they perceive the ſeveral motions of every ſeveral ſpirit that is in them, to receive the good, and deny the bad; nor can they know the ſeveral roots of Life and Death, which plant to pluck up, and which to feed on; and how can ſuch labour in Gods Vineyard? And indeed, without this Light the Body is a houſe of darkneſs, and a habitation of every deceitful ſpirit, and the heart deſperately wicked, and no man knows it, but he in whom the Light of Truth ſhineth; and he that declares to man his thoughts, his Name is the <hi>Lord of Hoſts.</hi> Thus is he the Head of the Corner, which the ſtumbler cannot compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend in his wit, and ſo rejects him, without whom there is no building, nor working the Work of God.</p>
            <p>And therefore you ſons of the darkneſs of this World, mind in your ſelves what it is you ſet your ſelves againſt; is it not that Light which would limit and chain the evil one in you, that which condemns you for every evil work, ſecret and open, which will not let you be proud and wanton, and luſtful? that which in your own hearts teſtifies againſt you for deceit and falſhood towards God, and towards men, deceit in Religion, hypocriſie and falſhood, making a form of what you are not? deceit in your dealing with men, in your tradings and ſpeakings, and ſeverall actings, both as Rulers, Prieſts and People, without reſpect of perſons, nor any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thing? but hath reſpect onely to that of God in you, which is
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:62428:5"/>
of his Nature, given to you to guide man in the Light of God, out of all the wayes of this deceiving ſpirit.</p>
            <p>And now he that comes to you with this Doctrine, comes near you, being manifeſt in Spirit to that of God in your own hearts, you are pricked therewith, and then the evil one is ſtirred up in you, to fight againſt that which is Truth in your ſelves, and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers to the Truth which is ſpoken to you, by another without you, from the ſame Spirit of Truth, which by you is rejected; And thus you joyning with him that riſes up in wrath againſt the Truth in your ſelves, and denying that which ſhould chain and bind the evil one, you deny the Lord of Life, and give ſtrength to the evil one to murther the Juſt in you, and quench the Spirit of Truth, and weary the Lord with ſtriving, till you be given up wholly to the power of darkneſs, who will then keep you ſeeking Salvation without, whileſt he is heaping up evil within.</p>
            <p>For that which ſeeks to devour your Souls is within you, whilſt he is leading you out to ſeek Salvation; and nought can damn you, but what is in you: ſin is within before it be acted, ſo muſt Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion be within before you be cleanſed; though the old deceiver hath taught people to think they are ſaved by believing God at a diſtance, who neither know nor worſhip him in the Spirit and Truth, nor are their bodies his Temples, nor can the Holy One dwell or walk in them, becauſe of uncleanneſs, but their Veſſels being filled with all the powers of darkneſs, and the heavenly Place with Spiritual wickedneſs, hath cauſed God to depart from the children of men for this uncleanneſs; and yet a Lyar ſpeaks Peace, and preaches Salvation, and the Creature believes ſo, being filled with darkneſs: But the Children of Light receive not this Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, who ſee and feel, and cannot be content with words, but with power. A talk of God ſatisfies not the Soul of a good man, till he feel his Preſence and Power; God without, and the Devil within, is not the Saints Faith nor Salvation; but God in them, and the Devil caſt out, is their glory and ſtrength, and they are bold through the might of his Spirit in them, to war daily againſt the Prince of this world, becauſe they know him who is greater in them and more holy, than he that is in the world. And this is the Faith-that overcomes the world; and he that's born of the Spirit, hath the Father and the Son, and he that hath the Devil is his Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:62428:5"/>
and knows him not whence he is, but judgeth him after the fleſh and outward appearance; but the Child of Light wars not after the fleſh, but after God, that he alone may have the glory, who is all in them that they have to glory in, who gives their ſouls the holy victory.</p>
            <p>And now, were not you wholly blind in your minds, and paſt feeling, you could never ſit down ſo beſotted, as to believe you are ſaved, while you are daily captivated in ſin, and forced many times to do that which you know you ſhould not, and this by the power of luſt in you, entiſing and leading you into every tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and cauſing to fall into many hurtful evils, which gathers ſtrength and rooting daily in you, heaping wrath and vengeance, by adding ſin unto ſin, which muſt all be accounted for in the end thereof, when you have filled your veſſels to a full meaſure; And can you ſay you are redeemed from the Devil, while he hath this power in you, that you are not able to reſiſt him, but are led cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive at his will, contrary to all fear of God, or power of Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs? Are your Bodies redeemed to God, and are you Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of Chriſt, whileſt you yeeld your members unto unrighteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs? or, are you ſaved who are ſervants of ſin? In what ſtands the life and power of your Redemption, of your Faith, and of your Salvation, ſeeing nought can ſtand in God but that which brings forth to him? Is not he in the bonds of iniquity, who is bound to bring forth iniquity? Is not he a ſervant of ſin, in whom it reigns? Is not he the child of bondage, who is bound to bring forth what the evil-one begets in him, and to ſerve him in what he moves him unto? Mind this, you who are born after the fleſhly ſpirit, who act according to his will, who worketh in your fleſh to bring forth unto death; Doth your profeſſion ſave you, who are not turned from dead works? The foundation of Repentance is not yet laid in you, and therefore death reigns above the Life that ſhould bring forth to God; and this is the ſervant of ſin's ſtate, and ſpirit of bondage, and not the Heirs ſtate, who inherits God's Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and brings forth thereof unto that Spirit, which pleaſeth God, as you bring forth to the fleſh, and pleaſe the world; And theſe two ſeeds are within, and are at enmity and diſagreement, and there can be no concord betwixt them, no more than light and darkneſs; and their ſeveral fruits are made manifeſt with the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:62428:6"/>
Light, which condemns the one, and confeſſeth the other to be of God, and wrought in God.</p>
            <p>And as many as are quickned with the Spirit of Life, have the feeling of this before they bring forth the fruits thereof into the world, and are come to the diſcerning of things that differ in na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and effect, by the taſting and handling of the Word of Life, and knowledge of that Election which is before the World was, by which they are made able to judge the ground and end of every motion in them, or to them; which abiding in, they need not man to teach them, neither can they be deceived; which makes them with boldneſs bring forth openly ſuch words and works as are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten in them by the Word of Life, which ſhews the whole World to lie in wickedneſs, and makes it manifeſt in the Light of Life, by whom the Prince of<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> this World is judged and condemned, and the ſecrets of hearts made manifeſt, according to the nature of eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſeveral ſpirit, which comes up to the day of the Lord's appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance. And to this Spirit of Truth muſt an account be given by all fleſh living; for this is he that lives to all generations, and is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changable in his witneſs againſt the evil ſeed, into whatever form he transforms himſelf, in words and profeſſion; yet is there no agreement betwixt their ſeveral natures, be they in one perſon, or be they in a family, or be it in a Nation, there is not agreement; nor can any one perſon Family or Nation ſerve them both, but who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever ſerves the one, hates the other, and condemns him: ſo he that ſerves Deceit, condemns the Juſt, and ſo condemns that which ſhould ſave him, and muſt judge him in the end. And here is the cauſe of that fleſhly liberty which ſome have got (for the preſent) where the Witneſs is ſlain; and alſo of the horrour of Conſcience, where the Juſt appears towards Judgment: the unſtable eſtate of ſuch who are faithful to neither, the everlaſting Peace and Power in ſuch where the Juſt hath dominion, and the preſent ſorrows of ſuch who are diligent in waiting and wreſtling to the end of the World, and the beginning of Chriſt Jeſus, through Faith and Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience; And all theſe are comprehended with him who hath lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Chriſt, by being faithful to that Spirit of Truth, ſent in his Name, to teſtifie what is of him in every veſſel, and what is of the ſpirit that luſteth againſt him, and keeps the Creation in bondage.</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:62428:6"/>
            <p>And this is that one way to Life and Salvation, holden forth freely by the Spirit of Truth, ſent forth by the Father in the Name of Chriſt Jeſus, who hath its ſeveral operations in ſeveral veſſels, according as he finds them towards God; in ſome he is a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demner<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> in ſome a Leader and Teacher towards God; in ſome a perfect Juſtifier, in the ſight of God preſenting them, who alſo gives ſeveral gifts, and power to ſuch as receive this Teſtimony of Jeſus Chriſt; yet is he but one in all, unchangeably Juſt, Equal and Holy, who by the Power of his Word changeth all things that are changeable, and bringeth all things to the beginning, before People, Nations and Tongues were divided, where man lives by the Spirit of a pure life.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Now all that deſire to be ſet free from this Bondage fore-mentioned, and from that Law of Sin and Death that hath its ſtrength in the fleſhly part, diligently mind to feel in your ſelves, as followeth.</head>
               <p>THE Spirit of Life which is in <hi>Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> by whom the World was made in the beginning, hath a Law that is Spiritual, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding from himſelf; which Law gives light in ſpirit to good and bad, teſtifying againſt the power of ſin and death; which Light, as many as receive by faith and obedience, are brought thereby under the Law of Life, which whoever is faithful in, are led in ſuch wayes, whereby that part in man in which the Law of ſin hath its power, is crucified and ſlain, and the Seed of the Covenant there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by comes to its right freedom, which by the man of ſin is kept in bondage, while the ſtrong man keeps the houſe, whoſe ſtrength is in ſuch things as the carnal mind takes pleaſure in; which things the Law of the Spirit calls them from, who mind it in the Light thereof, and leads to exerciſe the mind in ſpiritual things, and to feed on the Word of Life, whereby the inward man is ſtrengthen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and made to grow up into the ſtature of a ſpiritual man, filled thereby with ſpiritual power, life and vertue, to bring forth unto God, and to live to him, as the other lived to the fleſh and brought forth unto death.</p>
               <p>Thus the Spirit of Life draws with the Light, and ſaith, <hi>Come,</hi> to all that mind its Voice; and to as many as obey, he changeth and feedeth with the New, whereby they become New Creatures,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:62428:7"/>
born of Freedom; And the fleſhly ſpirit it draws, and ſaith Come, holding forth viſible Idols to take the carnal affections, and to cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivate the mind from the Spirit of Life into carnal objects, who promiſe much to the eye of earthly wiſdom, and have a likeneſs of a ſubſtance in them, but the end is death, and the whole life is captivity to vanity, and eternal ſeparation from God; And here are the Children of Freedom, which are in Chriſt Jeſus made ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt to the world, by their coming out of it; and the children of bondage manifeſt, who cannot deny to ſerve it; and betwixt theſe two is no agreement: for he that is a ſervant of ſin, is free from Righteouſneſs, &amp; the Servant of Righteouſneſs is free from ſin, and as he that is in the fleſh cannot pleaſe God, neither can he that is in the Spirit pleaſe the world: theſe are children of ſeveral King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms, and ſeveral Natures; And he that's born after the fleſh hath that ſpirit which luſteth enviouſly, and ſeeks to devour the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; and he that's born again after the Spirit of Life, is brought into the reſtoration, as in the beginning, and bringeth forth to God the Fruits of eternal Life and Salvation in the Creation.</p>
               <p>And as by the Creatures yeelding and conſenting to the ſubtile one, the life is loſt, and the evil ſeed gets ſtrength in man to rule and bring forth after the power of darkneſs; So by the Creatures believing in the Light, and by yeelding to the motions of the Life of Holineſs, and the Law thereof, comes the evil ſeed to loſe its ſtrength and feeding, which is upon carnal things; and that Life which is by Faith hearing, comes again to be renewed in the Veſſel, and ariſes through the Spirit, and reigns above death; and the Righteouſneſs and Virtue of that Life is not of the nature of fleſh and blood, but of God; and is made manifeſt in the earthen Veſſel, by the Life and Power of the Spirit, againſt the will of the fleſh, and the luſts thereof: And thus comes man again into the Reſtora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Redemption of the body, into the free ſervice of that Spirit and Life, of whom it is the off-ſpring, and for which, and by which it came into the world; and here is true reconciliation and peace with God, and no condemnation, but unity in Spirit and Life as the Father and Son are one, the luſt being ſlain, the enticer denyed, and the accuſer caſt out, and all things become new, and all things of God; here is no more the houſe of bondage to ſin, but the glorious liberty of the Sons of God; that Nature
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:62428:7"/>
being quickned that is Spiritual, it doth not feed on carnal plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, but upon God; ſo the inward man becomes a natural Branch of the holy Root, and a Plant of the living God, bringing out freely what the Root ſends forth, in which God is glorified, and the Veſſel made Honourable, and the Soul filled with Peace and fatneſs, and hath no more ſorrow and death to oppreſs it; And the Light and Life which is in Chriſt Jeſus, manifeſt in the Spirit of Truth, is the firſt and laſt in this work; and here is ſeen how un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natural man, driven from God, is become, to that pure Life which gives him breath and being, and would preſerve him from deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, who is ſo wholly fallen from it, and become contrary to it, in nature and judgment, that of all things in the world its the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt croſs to be guided by that Light which ariſes in him from that holy Life, and daily calls him in Spirit thereinto, being degene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated into a contrary nature, more ſubtile and ſelfiſh, is willing to joyn with the enemy thereof in any way againſt the pure Light that's in himſelf, it to revile, reproach, murther and turn into darkneſs, by covering it with deceit; though man in this ſtate hath nothing in him but it, that is of the Nature of God, Holy and Juſt, or that will call him from the paths of the deſtroyer, into the way of <hi>Life,</hi> or bring forth through him any Fruits of obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, or ſpiritual Worſhip that God will own; nor hath he any other thing in this world that is alwayes preſent with him, to give him to ſee when he is inticed with his luſts, and tempted to ſin, nor the way how to eſcape the temptation; yet is man ſo exalted in the contrary nature, that he hath forgotten his Creator, and lifts up the heel againſt the reproof of his Spirit, trampling upon the low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly motions of the Holy One, and the Law which out of his mouth proceeds, counting the Light and virtue of his Life to be a low and contemptible thing, not able to ſave. Thus doth loſt man daily deſpiſe the Spirit of Grace and Truth in the inward parts, and rejects the Holy Ghoſt againſt their own ſouls, and denies his pure and ſingle eye, and holy movings in them, by which the holy men of God ſpoke, ſaw and diſcerned in all Ages, as the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures do teſtifie; all which is loſt in that man who is exalted above the pure Light and lowly Spirit, in which God meets man to teach him the knowledge of the Truth.</p>
               <p>And therefore you Teachers and People of all ſorts and Sects,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:62428:8"/>
who ſo violently have ſet your ſelves againſt the Light of the Spirit within you, and within others, when it calls to you for a return to it; How long will you kick againſt that which pricks you at the heart for your contrary walkings, and diſſembling profeſſions? why will you not be ſtill and commune with it in your own hearts, that you might come to a true feeling, and diſcern what nature it is of, and from whence it is, and what way it works, and againſt what? And alſo what nature that is in you, which it chiefly condemns and works againſt, and from whence that is? that ſo with the Light of Truth you might come to judge things that differ in the ground, and in the end, that you might ſo come to walk in the Light, in Judgment, and in Truth of Heart towards God and man. And let the ſingle Truth of God without mixture anſwer theſe things following feelingly in you.</p>
               <p>What is the cauſe that while you are profeſſing to ſeek God and ſerve him, you ſhould be ſo unwilling to ſerve him in that which is of his own Nature, and to worſhip him in Spirit and Truth, in your own Veſſels, whoſe bodies ſhould be the Temples of God, who is not worſhip'd in Temples made with hands, nor in a na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture contrary to himſelf? Or will the talking of what he is or was in others, in whom he was known to walk and ſpeak, deliver your Souls from the power of the Prince of darkneſs and deceit, that is in your ſelves, unleſs you can by Faith receive him in you alſo, as they received him, and feel his Power overcoming and caſting out him that hath you captive at his will, againſt your Faith and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience? Or, will God be found in you, or accept your worſhip, whilſt his Temple is poſſeſſed with his enemy, and a contrary nature acts you therein? Can you meet with God in any thing but that which is Holy, who hears not the prayer of him that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gards iniquity.</p>
               <p>Wherefore your firſt work ſhould be to know him in you whom God accepts, for he alone muſt preſent you to the Father, who ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears without ſin; underſtand what I ſay, he that appears without ſin, elſe you are reprobate in Gods ſight; there is no hope without Chriſt in you and you in him, the everlaſting Prieſt, to offer up upon the Altar of atonement. Holineſs muſt make one in Spirit; and though by the height of your minds, he that is without ſin be low and little in you, yet <hi>without me you can do nothing,</hi> ſaith Chriſt
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:62428:8"/>
Jeſus; mind what he ſaith, you can do nothing; Then what are you doing who are not in the holy Spirit? Can you worſhip by Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, or be ſaved by the Letter? will you make Chriſt a lyar, who ſaith, Without me you can do nothing? <hi>I am the Light of the world; every branch</hi> (ſaith Chriſt) <hi>that abideth not in me, is caſt out, and withereth, and is for the fire;</hi> Mind this, you that reject holineſs in Spirit, and light, from the holy Spirit in you; Are you not cut off, who are not in that which is holy; are you not withered and for the fire? Are you not caſt out, who have no abiding-place in that which is holy, and a light in that which is holy? Mind what is withered in you, and what is fruitful; Have you power, light and knowledge in you to do evil, but not to do well? Are you not withered then unto God? are you not cut off from the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Son, and planted in a wild Vine of a contrary nature? Your light is withered, and your ſeed corrupted, and your tree is known by its fruits, which now is green and brings forth, but not to God, nor from God, who are cut off and withered; without light in you, without Chriſt in you, without God in you to keep you; not ſo much Truth in your inward parts as is able to teach you, &amp; to make you free: here is your loſs and nakedneſs manifeſt, and the ſhort bed, and the narrow garment, who have not ſo much of the holy Spirit as will cover you, nor bear you harmleſs. Now, will you ſay, you hope you are born again of the Spirit, and are baptized into the Spirit, and walk in the Spirit, and worſhip in the Spirit, and then are gone out for Salvation and Light, and ſpeak evil of that within, as not able to bear you againſt him that is of the world? Now your Hope is not an Anchor, nor your Faith in that which overcomes by birth, as the Saints do, <hi>Whoſoever is born of God, overcomes the World:</hi> And, <hi>he that is begotten of God, keepeth himſelf, that the evil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>one toucheth him not.</hi> Now mind, Where is he that keepeth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf? and where is the evil-one? Let Truth anſwer in you, if there be any knowledge of God in the houſe. Is not that he who gives you light, that would keep you from the evil-one? and ſhould you not be one in Him that would keep you from evil? Who is your Keeper? Watchmen that are blind. Do not you watch in vain, who know not the Lord to keep your City? elſe how ſhould the evil-one have his liberty in and out without a powerful reſiſting? conſider in your ſelves, Where is he that gives you to ſee when
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:62428:9"/>
the evil-one toucheth you, and when he tempteth but toucheth not? What nature is he of that doth this for you? and where is he? Is he not light and underſtanding, and is he not in you? and is he not of a contrary nature to the evil-one that tempteth? And doth he not ſhew you the temptation, before you conſent thereto, (if you mind him?) Then what is the cauſe that the evil is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, ſeeing a Light and Nature appears againſt him? Is it not becauſe you joyn to the evil-one, and like his motion better than his that teſtifies it to be evil? And ſo you deny the Holy-One and the Juſt, and become one with the evil-one; And then you ſay, The Light is not able, when you have denyed it, and have not been faithful to joyn to it in counſel and ſtrength, but have given your ſtrength to the contrary; but they that are born of it, do not ſo; but when they are ſhewed the evil-one and his temptation, be it what ever it be to, or under what pretence ſoever, if the Light teſtifies againſt it, Then is their diligence, watchfulneſs and ſobriety, uſed againſt it in the fear of God, leſt they ſhould be drawn from the Light and enticed; and with all their power they joyn in obedience to the way of the Light, ſo that there is a war and wreſtling ere the thing be over; and being reſiſted ſtedfaſt in the Faith, he flees, and the Glory returns to God who dwells in the Light. And if at any time the evil-one prevail, the creature comes to ſee the cauſe to be in himſelf, and not in God, and for it is humbled and warned; and this he comes to ſee when the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptation is over, and the enemy fled, and he is come again into coolneſs with God in the Light; which while the darkneſs was up, and the enemy in the houſe, he ſaw not.</p>
               <p>And thus is experience gained through tribulations and tryals, which they who endure not the temptations, never come to learn of God, but fall under the temptation through unfaithfulneſs to the Light, and ſo are ever captives at his will who tempts to evil, and the enemy of all Righteouſneſs ever reigns over all the Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, leading out the Eyes, Ears, Hands and Heart to iniquity and vanity, and the Tongue to plead for it, againſt every reproof; having denyed the reproof of the Spirit of Truth within your ſelves, it cannot be received from others, for in that houſe the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary ſpirit wholly reigns, which turns away the ear from hearing of Knowledge, and the heart from good underſtanding in Spirit.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:62428:9"/>And this is the cauſe why you are kept alwayes without the feel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of God and his Power, and knowledge of his Word, and the myſteries of his powerful Counſel are hidden from you, which he reveals to the faithful, who have overcome through Faith and Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience, in whom Satan is ſubdued and trodden under foot; for in whom this devourer is above, what ever God gives or reveals to the Creature, the Deceiver is ready to pervert it quite to a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary end, that God never intended in the giving thereof, and to lift up a wrong nature, and exalt a contrary ſpirit, which God hates; and this is evident in the Light of Truth throughout the World. What is the Gift of God which the ſpirit of the World abuſes not? If God give Wealth, where that ſpirit is above, how is the creature puft up therewith above the reſt of his brethren, as though he were no more of the ſame mould and blood, but as God would he be worſhipped; If he give beauty, its turned into luſt, pride and wantonneſs, begetting and deceiving adulterous eyes; Wiſdom is turned into folly and wickedneſs, ſcorning the ſimple, and over-reaching the plain-hearted, and ſuch as have moſt of it, are but moſt able to compaſs their corrupt ends; If God give Grace, its turned into laſciviouſneſs, and Gods long for bearance into hardneſs of heart; Religion and Profeſſion into a cloak for ſin and hypocriſie; Faſting and Praying, to accompliſh mens ſelf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ends againſt ſuch as they would ſwallow up, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And not one thing that God can give, which this evil one will not ſubvert and turn againſt the giver, ſo that though God be free in himſelf, and good and plentiful by Nature, yet he cannot ſo ſhew himſelf to ſuch in whom the ſtrong man keeps the houſe, who makes the creature thereby but more wanton to kick againſt his Creator, and puffs him up to forget his Maker and Feeder; and ſo a fruitful Land maketh he barren, for the wickedneſs of him that dwells therein, which from the beginning was not ſo.</p>
               <p>Neither is it ſo with the Children of Light and Counſel; who have the Giver in their hearts above the gift, where the pure Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel ſits to order the pure Gifts, where every good and perfect gift is brought forth in its own nature, form, and manner, undefiled, or disfigured with the ſpirit of the World; but the ſprings run forth from the clean Fountain, and the Plant and Fruit is Holy like the Root, where the ſpirit is clean, and the fleſh undefiled,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:62428:10"/>
and every thing as it comes from God, as in the beginning, where the world is ended, and the old man put off, and all things of God; there every gift of God is known by its fruits, and nature, and ends, in ſuch Veſſels; The Gifts of God return to God by glorifying him here on earth, where Riches bring forth good and merciful Works, and not pride and vain glory; Wiſdom ſtands up againſt Oppreſſion, and not to deceive; and through Grace doth Righteouſneſs reign unto Life eternal; their Religion is pure and unmixt with the World, but ſeparated from it, whereby the Sons and Daughters of God are known in the ſtreets, by his virtue and comelineſs put upon them by him, with which they are covered over, as a Garment, even with all the Fruits of the Holy Spirit of Faith and Truth, which is in Chriſt Jeſus, who is Lord over all in ſuch Veſſels; and theſe are the Veſſels of Honour ſit for the Lord to ſhine through againſt his adverſary (the worlds ſpirit) in Fruits that cannot be condemned, being not defiled in the Veſſel, but manifeſt as they come from above, anſwering to that of God in every heart, in which the evil one hath neither part nor power; theſe are Sons of God without rebuke, in the midſt of an unclean generation ſhining as lights; and this alone honours God, which is of God; and this anſwers the end of mans Creation, and Gods bounty, who is rich in ſuch, till they come to be filled with all the fulneſs of God, which he withholds not from ſuch; but from the unclean and ſlothful, ſuch who defile the fleſh with luſts, from ſuch he withholds his riches and fulneſs; therefore the World knows not the Sons of God, nor whence they are, nor whither they return, who follows Chriſt out of the World, never return<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thither again, but to teſtifie againſt it, whoſe Veſſels are no more filled with luſt, and the ſpirit of this World to bring forth thereto, but are filled with the holy Ghoſt, who hath made them new Creatures for himſelf to walk in, and ſhine forth in Fruits of the Spirit.</p>
               <p>And now you wild Colts, and barren earthly minded Profeſſors, who have filled your Veſſels with wantonneſs and deceit, and all ſorts of fleſhly minds; in vain do you hunt about with your old Bottles, and think to retain the Heavenly Treaſure, you gad a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout, but to no purpoſe in the ſight and eſteem of God, for you are in the wrong work, while you are in the worlds nature, and in
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:62428:10"/>
the old creation; your words and ordinances are empty of the Life of God, and his Fruits you cannot bring forth nor receive, till you be renewed; nothing you can do will avail you but a new creature; your old veſſels are full of the old wine from the wild grape; and that's above in you which defiles the pure, ſo God withholds his Gifts from you, which abound in his new Creation, and you know nought of it but what condemns you; ſo you fight againſt it, and ſay there is nothing now perfect, and ſo would con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn the new with the old, and judge them alike: and thus you err, not knowing the Gift of God, nor the Works of his Hands, which are all perfect as he is perfect, who walks not in the defiled temple, nor lies in the boſom of harlots, who are out of his power and perfect way of a holy Life; Therefore</p>
               <p>Your work would profit you moſt, to take the Candle of Truth, and ſweep the houſe at home, and caſt out the old leaven, and whatever is of the world, and wait in that which works in ſpirit againſt the old, till therewith all be made new; and the new veſſel which will not receive the old, nor mix with it; that is it which will hold with the new, which God will fill with himſelf; there the Seed may ſpring and not be devoured, and the Lilly grow without being choaked; There the Lamb may be ſafe from the Fox, and the pure from pollution; which can never be, while your covetous, proud, luſtful, earthly minds are alive in you, or ought that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with you have treaſured in, or grows up in that ground, the Plant of God is more pure and tender then to grow amidſt ſuch polluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; ſo to judgment you muſt firſt come, and own your condemna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion upon all the old, before you can receive of the new, or it grow in you. What agreement hath the Spirit of meekneſs with the ſpirit of pride, Contentedneſs with covetouſneſs, Holineſs with luſt, Chriſt with <hi>Belial,</hi> Light with darkneſs? Read and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand, here is the cauſe why you have ſought and laboured ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny years, and many of you further off then at firſt, but none hath found freedom indeed, nor that reſt where the Thief and unclear comes not to devour. Conſider theſe things while they are near you, leſt your hearts harden in you through unbelief, and the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit of luſts: And if you will come, then refuſe not him that calls and gives you light in the dark, but faithfully manage the watch and the war on his behalf with all your power, till all be brought
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:62428:11"/>
under <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> which he teſtifies againſt in you, and do not anſwer the Truth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> calls with deceit and excuſes, leſt he turn away from you, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> more worthy. If you ſay the world holds you back, then its time you ſhould not delay to break thoſe bonds that are grown ſo ſtrong already, they will be ſtronger every day, and what will the end be? Conſider &amp; underſtand like men, and ſay not, you have not ſtrength, but turn with that ſtrength with which you have long ſerved the world, and you will find God (that gave it you) the better Maſter; and the Redeemer is ſerved with leſs vigor than the ſpirit of bondage; and do but faithfully give the ſtrength you have of God unto the ſervice of God in the Light, and he requires no more then he gives; its deceit that makes theſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſes, and not a willing mind; and were you in the fear of God, theſe words you would not utter againſt your ſelves a witneſs; for theſe are not the words of children of love, nor obedient ſervants, but of ſuch as are without.</p>
               <p>Therefore in truth of heart conſider, what ſtate you are in, and who is your father, and hath power in you, who thus ſpeak; Can you do evil with both hands, live to your luſts, ſerve the world, compaſs the earth for your profits and pleaſures, with power, wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and delight; and have you not power to do well? Now ſhould you ſee your ſtrong captivity, and how you are degenerated from God, and the end of your creation, with your whole ſtrength, and become altogether reprobate to Gods ſervice; and for this ſhould your hearts be ſmitten with ſorrow, did you love God or his true Worſhip; and that evil tongue you would bridle, and your eyes you would limit from vanity, your ears from pleaſure, and your hearts from deceit, that ſo you might only hearken to the Light, if by any means you might come to hear the voice of him that's ſent into the world, to call you from under the power of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan unto the living God, by preaching Light to you who ſit in Darkneſs, and are dead while you live; neither can you be quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned till you hear the Voice of the Son of God, which the deceiver keeps you from in your worldly pleaſures, long prayers, and a ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing profeſſion, taking the Saints words to cover you from true judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but have not their Spirit nor Power to live their lives; nor are you Plants of that Root and Nature which brings forth to God, as he is, in whom there is no change: And this is not the Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:62428:11"/>
that God accepts, which is brought in the unclean Veſſel with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out his power and renewed ſtrength.</p>
               <p>Wherefore that nature which is become ſo wholly unprofitable, ſhould be denyed its will, and its way ſtopt; and to that ſeed you ſhould dye which rules in that ſtrength you have, and runs to and fro to ſeek for its ſelf, but ſeeks not God firſt; and to that which is pure muſt you turn, and therein wait for the Anointing, and the riſing of the holy Seed; for it's the moſt holy that muſt be anointed in you, ere you can know Chriſt in you; and <hi>without Chriſt you can do nothing;</hi> and that ſeed which is neither willing nor able, is not he, but is the ſeed of the evil-doer, as is mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt by his fruits, which muſt be denyed, his thoughts, his words, his profeſſion, his prayers, his luſts, his ſin and his righteouſneſs; for it's all of one nature, and ſtands up in you to withſtand the coming of the Seed of the Covenant, Chriſt Jeſus the Life of God and Light of Men, which hath Gods Power which was in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning, Gods Righteouſneſs, and is to all generations; whom the Heavens muſt retain, until the end of all theſe things, and the reſtitution of the Creation to God, till which you cannot know his appearance in you without ſin, who died for ſin.</p>
               <p>Whoſe Light (as is before declared) ſhews you his Law, and the Spirit of Propheſie teſtifies of him to come, whoſe way before his face muſt be prepared (if you have ears to hear and underſtand;) and all your crooked, untoward, wanton wayes muſt be made ſtreight, and your hidden ſubtile wayes made plain; and the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finers fire muſt paſs through your houſe, and take hold on all that will burn, till it be conſumed; for till the filth be purged out, and an end made of ſin, God comes not to his Temple, nor is ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Righteouſneſſe brought in for an Inheritance to eternal Life.</p>
               <p>And here will you come to learn the firſt Principle of pure Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion and Doctrine of the beginning of Chriſt; and the founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Repentance from dead works will be laid in you, then will you ſee what kind of treaſure your wanton careleſs minds have treaſured up in your veſſels, &amp; your deceitful &amp; unprofitable words and works, you will then ſee, by that which will not lie; then will you find that all will fail but Truth; and what you have ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered by craft and deceit, will ſtand in no ſtead but to deceive
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:62428:12"/>
you: Truth in the inward parts muſt be your ſtay, if any you find, for to that Rock you will be forced to fly, in the end for refuge, when all elſe is weighed and found too light to abide the tryal, though now it be lightly eſteemed, and you ſay its not able to ſave; its that within that muſt give you the knowledge of God in the face of Jeſus, nought without you will make your peace, but that which works in you, that muſt cleanſe the houſe of your ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſary, and ordain peace for you.</p>
               <p>And this is that which makes the holy men of God, who have gone before you in this Regeneration, to preſerve a clean Houſe and a pure Conſcience, above all that the World can afford or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, knowing that in the day of tryal all will prove a lye, but what is truth in the inward parts; and that none are true worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers but who worſhip the Father in the Spirit and in Truth; and the whole myſtery of Faith and of Godlineſs is learned within, and holden in that which is pure; and <hi>the pure in heart onely ſees God,</hi> and have heard and learned of him; and ſuch are Sons indeed, who are born of the Spirit, and led by the Spirit, and filled with the Spirit: and theſe have power, light and underſtanding to do well, who have God in them, who is holy, and that Spirit which the Devil is not able to reſiſt; and every Child of God hath this in their meaſure, by which they reſiſt the World and overcome it, even that which is born of God; that onely overcomes, which is faithful and will not forget himſelf: bleſſed onely are they who have of this in them in the evil times, which God cannot forget, nor ſuffer to be tempted above meaſure, ſuch only have that Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, for whoſe ſake the fleſh is ſaved: and in this only doth the creature find favour in the ſight of God in the day of vengeance, when God ariſeth to plead with all the earth for their wickedneſs; a Seed ſhall be ſaved, but that is not it which ſaith and doth not.</p>
               <p>And therefore think of this, all you who mock at a pure Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and reject that of God within, and ſpeak lightly and reproach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully of it; did you know whom you reproach, and againſt what it is you ſport your ſelves, you would rather gnaw your tongues then utter a word againſt it; you would change your minds, and ſeek it with thoſe that ſell all, that they may find it; though it be little in you, ſo that you dare not truſt to it, yet all that have pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved it, prize it as the great Power of God to Salvation; and whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:62428:12"/>
you can receive it or no, you have no Election but what is in it: In this did <hi>Noah</hi> find grace in the ſight of God, when the earth was corrupted, and <hi>Noah</hi> walked with God, and was juſt and perfect in his generation, and in that which was juſt and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect he was ſaved; and in the Righteous Seed which was grieved with the uncleanneſs of <hi>Sodom,</hi> was <hi>Lot</hi> ſaved. Now if you can read your Election you may, its onely that which was before ſin was, that is grieved at ſin, and teſtifies in man againſt unclean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; and this Seed ſtands elect before the world was; if you can receive it, and make it ſure, you may, but you which ſay, you have not power to do well, and denies his Call, can never do it.</p>
               <p>He that calls out of ſin, and the ſoul that is vexed becauſe of ſin, is little and lowly in you; but the god of this world is lofty, ſtrong and powerful in you, and hath lifted up your hearts on high, to ſeek great things far above that pure principle of true light and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, which God hath choſen and elected to himſelf, and wherein he will commune with man, and teach him his fear and knowledge, and give him renewed ſtrength, and of his ſpiritual power, and ſalvation from ſin,</p>
               <p>And now your lofty looks are too high for this door, and the day of this ſmall and ſimple one you deſpiſe; theſe waters are too ſtill for you to drink on, and to ſtay and wait for great things where ſo little is ſeen, you have not faith; ſo you out-run your reſt, and the poor in Spirit take the Kingdom before you, to whom the Election and Bleſſing belongs. Now conſider, you that are lofty, rich and high-minded, mind the Calling of God and his Election; Hath he elected the rich in notion, and high in profeſſion, the proud and the wanton? Hath not he choſen the weak and poor, fooliſh and contemptible to confound all this? But he doth not confound the Election, the poor, lowly and meek; the pure and holy in heart and ſoul he doth not confound nor ſhut out, but he that is pure, meek, and holy, calls; and the ſoul that is meek, lowly, and loves holineſs, it anſwers in all converſation, obtaining grace to be holy, as he that calls is holy. Here is the Calling made ſure, and the Election by anſwering thereto, who keeps in the Call, and in the Election, which was in God before tranſgreſſion was; But you that deny him that calls you out of darkneſs into light, by the power of his holineſs, lowlineſs, meekneſs and truth, mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:62428:13"/>
in Spirit in you, according to the gift of God in his tender mercy, by which this ſprings from above, as was in the beginning; I ſay, you that reject this, to lay hold on ſomething that is ſet up without you ſince the beginning, you deny your Calling and Electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and betake your ſelves to a changeable thing, which the Electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is not, nor he that calleth thereunto: For the Election hath been preſerved in God, when all the world elſe, profeſſions and people have been deceived, defiled, deſtroyed and changed. And that is it which is alwayes pure (as God is pure) and changeth not; and he that goes out from this, doth not make it ſure to himſelf, by well-doing; For the Election is in the light and power of Holineſs and Truth, which they that ſay and do not, are out of.</p>
               <p>Therefore return from off the Mountains, you that have lift up your ſelves on high without God, who have a form without the power of God; And feel after that which is pure, lowly and juſt in you for God is a Spirit, and in the Spirit and Truth is he known and ſerved, and there is his counſel received, in that which is truth in your inward parts; feel that which never ſinned near you, then you draw near to God in Spirit, and keep there, and wait and hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken (what the Spirit ſaith, which never ſinned) with that princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in you which would not ſin, with that wait upon the holy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and mind his motion continually, and be obedient thereto, that you may once come to ſerve the living and not the dead, that you may be able to ſay, your Redeemer liveth, and that you know him, and have heard his Voice that is holy, as God is holy, that is lowly and meek; and that you have learned, and do alwayes learn of him, and are joyned to him, that you may become conformable to him that liveth and ſinneth not; And this appearance will be your daily Salvation and Peace, and daily growth and encreaſe in God; and make this ſure to you, in that principle which would not ſin for gaining the whole world, ſo ſhall you not loſe your E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection nor your Calling, but an entrance thereby will be daily mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtred into the Kingdom everlaſting, which is in Chriſt Jeſus the Light, and Truth, and Power of God.</p>
               <p>But if you go out to any other thing for help or counſel, then that Spirit which is pure, which is juſt, which is meek and lowly by nature, as God is, which is righteous by nature, and ſprings in you to bring forth fruit of it ſelf, to God alone, in that principle
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:62428:13"/>
which is pure and clean; then you go from the fountain of living waters to dig for your ſelves, and into your own works, and what you bring forth is your own righteouſneſs, and not that which is revealed from above, to all generations of God elected; And you will go through your work hard beſtead, and when you have brought it forth, it will not ſatisfie that in you which hungers towards God and is of him, onely it will puff up that nature which is ſelfiſh, and exalt that which is too high already to receive life from God; and this righteouſneſs God accepts not, nor is it everlaſting to all ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerations, which is brought in by works and not by vertue of the Divine nature ſpringing freely in you from an eternal Spirit, which thoſe who are entred into reſt, and keep the Sabbath holy, are free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly fed with, and covered over, who are ceaſed from their own works, whoſe works are wrought in God, and in him are brought to light, where the holy Child is born, and the Son of God mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt, through that Spirit which the World neither ſeeth nor know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, which gives to ſee and inherit God and godlineſs in a clean nature and veſſel.</p>
               <p>Which Birth if you deſire to be born of, then ceaſe from fleſh and blood, and what ever that can do for you within and without that is defiled; and in that which calls and convinceth you of ſin, wait and be faithful, till you find a life and deſire quickned in you; which can ſavour or delight in nothing, but that which is as God is, pure, juſt and holy, and loaths whatever is contrary, and cannot joyn to it in thought word nor action; for this is the life of the holy Child, if ever you feel it move and breath in you, and that ſpiritual birth which as it grows in the veſſel, is to be heir of the heavenly treaſure, which though at firſt it be weak as a child without underſtanding or full ſtrength; and you not knowing what way it is ever like to come to have all the power and domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in you, by reaſon of the abundance of corruption that is above in you, and the ſtrong bonds of iniquity that rules in your fleſh, which all war againſt the reſurrection of this Innocent life, and by which the ſtrong man keeps the houſe, with much ſubtilty and ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual wickedneſs, againſt the pure and ſimple life; yet if you do but abide in that which firſt gave you light to the quickening of it, and be obedient thereto, it will bring you a way you know not; and though you may come through great travels and temptations,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:62428:14"/>
and many fiery tryals and tribulations, where you may come to be ſifted and winnowed, yet ſhall not one grain of that pure Seed pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh and fail in the way, for that Spirit of light and truth will lead you in his light and in his truth, which hath been tryed in that way for many generations; for this is he that comes in the Name of Chriſt Jeſus, the Light and Salvation of Ages, who hath over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the Devil and the world, and all the power of darkneſs, for all that are ſanctified; and now is come to do it in you, that you may inherit your purchaſed poſſeſſion, and ſit with him in heavenly places alſo: ſo that your work is faith and obedience, and patience towards him who is that Spirit and Light in you; and to him muſt you give up life and all, who will confound your corrupted wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and blind his adverſary, that he may give light to that Seed that's yet under the ſhadow of death, and build up in you the way of peace; and you ſhall no more live by your works and gifts na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural; but becauſe he liveth in you, ſhall you live alſo; and your life will be that which is begotten of God which never dieth; and this will he do for as many as give up themſelves wholly to him, whoſe light leads out of ſin; this is the King of Saints, and holy Life, if you will receive him, he hath the Power of God.</p>
               <p>But you that pray and profeſs, and ſeek abroad, and cry for help, but know not him who hath help in his hands for you, in him alone to wait, that in all things you might obſerve him, you worſhip you know not what, nor where; and while in words you talk of God that liveth, in works you deny him, and give your ſtrength to the dead and not to the living. Should not every man know his God liveth in him, and go to his own God for life, according to the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtation of the Spirit of Truth given to profit withal, in every creature to Godward? And this God that liveth, who is juſt, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and true, ſhould you hear and know, and learn of, not of dead forms, but the power of the Spirit of life, whoſe Word giveth life to as many as have that ear open to hear the living ſpirit, and can ſavour the living from the dead: Now what ever you look to for life and ſalvation, which is not in this ſpirit and power, it's that which kills and devours your ſtrength to no purpoſe; for no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing gives life but the Spirit, it's the pure Spirit that feeds the hungry ſoul with bread of life; and to that you ſhould give up all you have and are: in hearkening and obeying ſpend your time, and
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:62428:14"/>
all your ſtrength to encreaſe in the life that's bread indeed: but when you give your ſtrength to cuſtoms and forms, and carnal ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diments, vain pleaſures and delights, and ſet your minds on theſe viſible things, then you ſpend your ſtrength for that which is not bread, and labour for that which profits not to life eternal, nor can carnal things give you an entrance into the moſt Holy; but in that which is pure ſhould you wait, that he may open to you the door of life; <hi>I am the Door, the Truth, and the Life,</hi> ſaith Chriſt Jeſus; who is not carnal, who is pure, clean, and lowly, and meek in ſpirit, who is in you except you be reprobates; <hi>and if any man have not the Spirit of Chriſt, he is none of his.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Minde and conſider well, the Spirit of Chriſt in you, that's he lowly in you, that's meek in you, that's juſt and holy in you; mind this Spirit in you, and then whither will you run, and forſake the Lord of Life; will you leave Chriſt the Fountain which ſhould ſpring in you, and hunt for your ſelves? ſhould you not abide with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, and drink of that which ſprings freely, and feed on that which is pure, meek and lowly in ſpirit, that ſo you might grow ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al men into the ſame Spirit, to be as he is, the ſheep of his paſture? for as is your paſture ſo are you filled. High carnal minds ſeek high things, and ſo they grow lofty and proud, and ſuch God reſiſts, and keeps them afar off; but the poor in ſpirit ſeek truth and meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and are fed thereof at the table of the Lord; meek and lowly, and juſt, and faithful are all his houſhold, who feed and ſup with him. Now mind and conſider your wayes, who are gone out un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the mountains to worſhip and feed your ſelves, you may read of Iſraels ſin in going out from the Temple, in which the Lord had ſaid he would dwell and be enquired of, and they builded Altars without him, and there called upon him, but found him not, for which he rejected their Worſhips, and their Temple alſo; And where hath Chriſt ſaid he will now be worſhipped, is it not within? for ſaith Chriſt, <hi>the true worſhippers worſhip the Father in Spirit and in Truth;</hi> mind it Profeſſors, not at <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> will he be enquired of, but in ſpirit and truth; and the body is the Temple, as he hath ſaid, <hi>I will dwell in them, and walk in them;</hi> and <hi>I will put my Law in their inward parts, and all ſhall know me, from the leaſt to the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt.</hi> Not in Temples made with hands doth the Godhead dwell, whoſe off-ſpring we are; not in your high places, and Steeple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:62428:15"/>
Churches, but in that which ſprings of him<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Can you read this and underſtand it aright? in that which ſprings of him, is the Godhead and Power known, but the high-minded are too far off it to feel it; it's the poor and lowly in ſpirit that are near it, and he that's become as a little child can only underſtand it, who is not too great in his thoughts to hearken to that which is little and pure in him; by birth and nature that ſprings of God, and not the height of that mind which hath Notions Divine, but not Nature, Life, and Sonſhip begotton and born of God. A ſanctified life and veſſel is God's off-ſpring; but he that ſaith and doth not, is not born of Truth, but of Fornication and Falſhood: ſo read your birth and nature, and kindred, with the Truth: It's not the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>circumciſed in heart, nor the baſtard, that's God's Off-ſpring and Child of his Love, but the pure and clean in heart, mind and ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, hath his Image. And if you look to be godly, you muſt know this in you, elſe you are without God in the world, having neither ſeen him nor known him whom you ſeem to worſhip, but are alie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated from him in your minds, and in your members, and in your whole ſtrength; ſo that you have neither power nor underſtanding to do well, being taken captive of a contrary ſpirit in all your abilities of ſpirit, ſoul, and body, your wiſdom perverted, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtandings darkned, and parted from the root, whoſe off-ſpring man is.</p>
               <p>And now this ſhould be your return; to ſink down to that which is holy and pure in the Light, and to that give up your whole man, and all you are and have; and no more conſult with your wiſdom, nor follow your own underſtanding, but let the little thing in you that's pure and ſimple, lead you, and thereto bow and bend and confeſs; And this will be your reſtoration to God, to give all you have to the Holy, who when he hath befooled your curſed wiſdom, and brought down your high conceits, and bound the ſtrong man, and tyed the colt to the vine; then will he ariſe in power, who is meek and holy, and rule in your ſtrength, parts, and wiſdom, having purged the enmity out, and renewed your abilities; and you will have all reſtored again manifold, all new, and clear, and able, by the power of the Holy One who will reign and govern therein; and you ſhall know the Lord, whoſe off-ſpring you are, to be both root and head, and all in you; and you ſhall ſay no
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:62428:15"/>
more, I am weak and can do nothing, but all things through him that gives you ſtrength: for the devourer ſhall no more pervert it, but great ſhall be the Holy one in the midſt of you, if this you can believe and receive; And you ſhall no more, as you have done, ſow for the devourer, nor bring forth unto blaſting, but your fruits ſhall ariſe to God, who will receive them with good will; and your prayers ſhall not return empty, when he hath bent you for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and taken away the accurſed from amongſt you; And then will you know the Lords Redeemed, and that Seed which is elected and bleſſed, which brings not forth as other men, and you will ſee that all who deſpiſe the day of ſmall things, neglect their own mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy (to follow the teacher of lies) who turns not at his reproof who is holy, and therefore worſhip without power.</p>
               <p>Then will you know the life and power of Redemption, and Sanctification, and Juſtification, and renewing of the Holy Ghoſt in you, when your ſtrength is redeemed to God, your wiſdom re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed, your hearts, tongues, eyes and ears, and all you have redeemed into God, into that which is holy, to be guided and exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed in all your converſation, poſſeſſing your veſſels in Sanctifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: Here is that renewing of the holy Ghoſt known, which ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies and juſtifies through the redemption of the bodie and mind, and reconciliation which is in Chriſt Jeſus, who is not known to be Lord but by the holy Ghoſt; that Spirit of Truth which leads into all Truth; which Truth is a witneſs in you, againſt you, who ſay you are redeemed to God by Chriſt Jeſus, when another Lord rules in you, and leads you captive into ſin, by which Chriſt Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus is denied and ſuffers in you, and by which you are ſeparated from God, and in a nature contrary to him: wherefore to that muſt you come which changeth your nature, and not your words, and forms, and teachers, but which begets another ſeed, and kills that which is begotten of whoredom and luſt, which is after the Prince of this World; that God may be ſerved in his own Spirit, in his own Truth, of his own nature, of his own begetting, Holy as he is Holy in every meaſure and growth thereof; that ſo the leaſt of his Children may be known to be of him, and ſeparate from the world, in ſoul and in body, coming out of the world, bearing his image and reproach.</p>
               <p>And as many as honeſtly deſire to be heirs of this holy Power and
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:62428:16"/>
Kingdom, patiently wait till you feel that move in you which is of this pure Nature; and having felt it alive in you, rejoyce in it with hope and faith, and keep therein, and be not diſcouraged becauſe of the littleneſs of it in your preſent ſight, neither do you judge and meaſure it thereby; for you know<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>not what power it hath with God, and how precious it is in his ſight; and what it will obtain for you at his hands in the time of need, you have not yet proved, nor can you, while you have things greater in your thoughts than it to run to: the power of Holineſs and Truth in the inward parts is not known but in the depth, when the fire of wrath comes upon all vain hopes, and hypocritical confidence, when all that is without a man is removed far away; when all relations, friends and acquaintance are become farther off than ſtrangers, and what-ever thing the creature ſeeks to for comfort, turns againſt him, and adds to his grief; then is known the power of Holineſs and Truth in heart with God, and a clean Conſcience will ſpeak peace; and none can take it away from you if you abide but in it: He that hath proved it, commends it to you who have been ſtript of all, that ye might learn and know the treaſure of life and holineſs with God; wherefore judge not that which is holier and lower then your ſelves, but let that which is juſt and holy, judge that which is above it in you, which is not of that nature.</p>
               <p>The cauſe why it is ſo little eſteemed in you, is, becauſe you are ſo great in the contrary nature; and the proud deſpiſes the poor, and the rich undervalues him that is better then himſelf. And this you will find in you, if you meaſure with that which God eſteems and weighs all fleſh by (to wit) by that which is his own, and as he is in every creature; ſo do not you judge the moſt Holy, but believe and obey; for the time for you to judge is not yet come, till the moſt Holy and Juſt be King in you, and you in him; ſo keep in that which is holy and juſt, and grow in him, that he may grow in you, and ariſe through death of his enemies to be greater then the greateſt, greater then the World, and the Prince of it, which is the Devil, wherein is all unbelief, falſe fears and doubting, and exaltation againſt the Holy One; and as theſe Tow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers fall which are lifted up againſt the Lord, ſo his way will become a plain, and Truth will take his place in you as King and Lord, which God loves, which the unbelief is out of and againſt; and
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:62428:16"/>
as the Pure ariſes, you will find a change in your mind, in your nature, in your judgment, and in your government, and you will come to know that your kingdom and power with the higheſt, ſtands in the anointing of the moſt Holy, and the Kingdom of God is within you, and the poor takes it.</p>
               <p>So you muſt not fix your faith upon that which is great and ſtrong in you, becauſe it is ſo, nor becauſe it is likely, nor becauſe it promiſeth great things; but believe in that which is moſt holy, true and juſt in you, that to the Anointing of the moſt Holy you may come in your particular, and he will bring you into the Aſſembly of the Sanctified, where the Holy One reigneth over all; for it's he that's ſent out into the world that lies in wickedneſs, to gather them one by one into Sanctification, therein to preſent unto God as many as receive him, who is without ſpot or blemiſh.</p>
               <p>And all the world take notice of this, where ever it comes, this is He whom the Father of Lights hath now ſent into you that are in the world; the Holy One of God ſent to call you and give you light, who ſaith, <hi>I am the Light of the World;</hi> Hear him, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, that you may become Children of Light and Truth: this is the glad-tydings and Goſpel of Jeſus Chriſt, who is preached to you in the world. Profeſſions, and forms, would limit the Holy One to themſelves, and exclude others; but Gods gift is free in Chriſt Jeſus, and his tender is to all men; <hi>who would have all men to be ſaved, and come to the knowledge of the Truth;</hi> none he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes, none but who will not receive his gift, his Son, the moſt Holy which calls you, who through the preaching of the Goſpel is come near you; yea, he is in you with his Light, giving you to ſee the way out of darkneſs, which no other thing could do for you; and without money or price you have him: If you receive him and keep his ſayings, and obey his movings, He will dwell in you, and take up his aboad, and you ſhall know that the Father hath ſent him to call you out of the world into the Light of Life; if you de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Him, he will deny you; If you receive Him, the Father will love you, and power from above will be given to become the Sons of God. Wherefore mind that Spirit which calls you out of ſin, out of the world, and gives you light to ſee what is ſin and deceit in your own hearts; hearken to that which is Holy, and would not have you do evil, that's of the Holy One, and the moſt Holy in
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:62428:17"/>
you, believe in Him and follow Him; believe not them who would make you believe you have him not in you, who are paſt feeling in themſelves, and have already rejected him; but you who feel him, abide in him, who is holy in you, againſt all unholi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs a witneſs; cut not your ſelves off through diſobedience and unbelief, and he will in no wiſe caſt you out, but will encreaſe your light through obedience, and purifie your ſouls, and cleanſe your bodies, and work in you mightily in Truth to Salvation; and you ſhall ſee that his working is pure and good, and that which none elſe can do for you; and this is <hi>the Lord your Righteouſneſſe,</hi> though yet you know him not as he is.</p>
               <p>And if you will receive the moſt Holy, this is your time and the day of your viſitation by him, whoſe Light is now rejected of the builders of this world, and the wiſdom of the wiſe will not know him, nor ſuffer him to rule above their carnal rudiments; nor to be all in their hearts to guide with his Light to Salvation; ſo to the out-caſts he is preached, who are afar off, and have not ſought him: You is he ſeeking with his Light; if you reject him not, he will make you to ſee Light who have ſat in the region of death: and groſs darkneſs hath covered you; wherefore hearken to him that ſaith Come, and feel that Spirit that draws, that you may anſwer his love freely, as it is freely tendred; and know him by his holineſs, that it is he; and let his uuchangeable witneſs in you in the night and in the day, perſwade your hearts, that he is the Lord who changeth not; and he that declares unto man his thoughts, his name is <hi>the Lord of Hoſts.</hi> And you that withſtand this appearance in Spirit, and tell people that this is not to preach Chriſt, and yet profeſs Chriſt in you, tell me what Chriſt is in people, if not Light and holie Life, and a faithful Witneſs againſt the contrary in all in whom he liveth, and by what other thing he may be known in ſpirit, life, and power, if this be denyed? elſe let the mouth of Antichriſt be ſtopt, that the ſimple may paſs on the right and living way, free from ſuch who will neither enter the Kingdom themſelves, nor would ſuffer others, who have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways reſiſted the holy Ghoſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:62428:17"/>
               <head>Alſo the fruit of the free-born cleared from legal performances, and the children of bondage ſhewed the nature of their own works.</head>
               <p>Children of this world, who have the form but not the power of Godlineſs, and have got notions of life, but not the nature and ſpirit thereof, in your dark thoughts from an unfruitful ſpirit you judge the Children of Light; and when you ſee us acting in the life of Chriſt Jeſus, then you ſay we are under legal performances, and that we think to be ſaved by our works, and that we do it to merit, and the like; but you are greatly miſtaken in your ſelves, and are not in that Spirit which doth ſee us, or can judge the nature of our works, nor our end therein; wherefore be ſilent, and hear what is ſaid to you, if you have an ear to hear withal: for though your ſelves be dead, withered branches, cut off from the tree which is good by nature, and there abide, yet it is not ſo with ſuch as are born again and ingrafted into the good Olive; for he that is really born of God, knows two ſeveral ſeeds and natures, which ſpring and bring forth from ſeveral roots, and after their ſeveral kinds.</p>
               <p>Now the firſt of theſe is in bondage with its branches, and brings forth unto ſelf, from ſome outward obſervation or litteral com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, or ſomething that is carnal or viſible ſets on work; and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thus ſet on work to do things contrary to your life and nature, you go hardly through it; and if you attain the outward perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance, the boaſter gets up to glory in what you can do, who doth all for ſelf-ends, and ſo looks for reward above ſuch as you think cannot do as you have done. Now you who have gone no further, but wearied your ſelves herein, and found nought but bondage, are turned back into liberty again; and you judge as you have found in your ſelves, ſo you ſay all good works are from the ſpirit of bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage, boaſting, and merit, and the like.</p>
               <p>But you ſhould not judge the Children of Light after the fleſh, your meaſure will not reach that birth; for he that's born of God, is a branch of another root and ſeed then you know, which hath another nature, inclining to God from whence it is, as the firſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clines to the world whence it is: And as the natural man doth evil naturally with delight, his root and life being ſo; So the ſpiritual
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:62428:18"/>
man (in his meaſure) doth good naturally after his root and life, which is his pleaſure and joy to bring forth from the good root, that which is good by nature; as it is the delight of the other to bring forth that which is evil by nature: for as is the heavenly, ſuch are they that are heavenly; and its no bondage for the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly to bear heavenly fruits, but to the earthly man it is, being againſt his nature: wherefore ſaith Chriſt, <hi>either make the tree good and his fruits good, or the tree evil and his fruits evil;</hi> ſo good trees, evil trees, and fruitleſs trees, are known to be of ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral natures, and for ſeveral ends.</p>
               <p>So this is but your own darkneſs that thus thinks, and with evil thoughts you judge amiſs. Will you ſay of ſuch as are really planted into the living Vine, that their fruits which freely ſpring from thence, are legal and bondage, and that we think to be ſaved by our works, and by our own righteouſneſs, <hi>&amp;c.?</hi> Nay theſe are the fruits of ſuch who are ſaved already: and the Righteouſneſs of God is given to us who are ceaſed from our own works, whoſe works are no more legal but ſpiritual, free and not bondage; and he thats in Chriſt is fruitful in good works, and free therein by birth; and he that abides in Chriſt, ſins not, nor is his ſeed of the evil doer. Could you underſtand this, you would not condemn the fruits of the living, with ſuch as are dead while they live, whoſe fruit is withered, being broken off from that which is good by na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and planted into that which is wild by nature; but the ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual man you cannot judge his fruits nor freedom, his off-ſpring, nor his end; whoſe fruits judge all fruitleſs trees, yet is he judged of no man: and it's as hard for you to do good, who are accuſtom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to do evil, as the Leopard to change his ſpots; but it is other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe with ſuch as are changed already, born of the Light, and heirs by birth, and right nature, to everlaſting Righteouſneſs and Truth, it's hard for ſuch to do evil, being againſt Nature, Seed and Son<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip which is in God: and though this you cannot believe, yet he thats born of Faith can, and the leaſt Child of God can read it in his meaſure, who knows the old <hi>Adam</hi> and the new; and as in the firſt all are in ſin and bondage, ſo in the ſecond are all made righteous and free to Gods work; and in the ſecond is known the new Creation wherein dwells Righteouſneſs, as God hath ſaid, <hi>I will dwell in them, and walk in them:</hi> And will you call this ſelf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteouſneſs,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:62428:18"/>
where all things are of God, and all things new? is this legal and bondage? And if any man be in Chriſt, all things are of God, and its God that worketh in us of his good and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure to will and to do; and this is not the ſpirit of bondage, but good will and pleaſure which God worketh freely in us; So you reproach what God worketh by the hearing of faith, and not by the letter, which righteouſneſs wrought in <hi>Abraham,</hi> which was in God before <hi>Abraham</hi> was, which is wrought for everlaſting, and elect of God in Chriſt Jeſus before the world was, and is a free gift to all that by <hi>Abrahams</hi> faith come out of the world, to him who is not of the world; which you that abide in the world inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit not, who are in ſelf; and ſeeking your ſelves in what you do to God or men, <hi>how can you believe,</hi> ſaith Chriſt? And you that look for rewards, are not in that Spirit which worketh freely: So you look for rewards and honour; teachers and people are all for rewards, honour, and reſpect of perſons; and in that nature is all the bondage, merits and rewards, in this nature out of the faith of Chriſt Jeſus, who went from place to place doing good freely, and preaching freely; and ſo will all do who are born of freedom, as he is free, whoſe life you ſpeak evil of, but know it not by birth and virtue, which is naturally good, as the firſt man is naturally evil.</p>
               <p>And the bondage is in that which is againſt the pure nature, and not in that which is free-born; and the law is upon the tranſgreſſor, and him that is degenerated into that nature which is carnal and ſenſual; and if this man do any thing as to God, it is from ſomething that is laid upon him, not in ſpirit, but from without; and this is legal and in bondage, which is not in the free Spirit, which doth by nature the things contained in the Law.</p>
               <p>And little it is that ſuch would either do or know, were there not a Law or a Letter, a Heaven or a Hell to put them upon works; and here is the bondage and fear that hath torment: but with the Spiritual Seed it is not ſo, who are begotten and born of God in Chriſt Jeſus, in whom they receive freely as the branch of the root; and what he ſends forth through them is fruits of the Spirit, againſt which there is no Law; and this is not legal, but ſpiritual and free, who are a Law unto themſelves; and there is no Law againſt the Seed, but is added upon the tranſgreſſor becauſe of ſin,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:62428:19"/>
till the Seed be come; and where the Seed is born and rules, that creature is not under the law, letter, nor tradition, nor bondage, but led by the Spirit, and born of that Nature which was before tranſgreſſion was, by which the fruits of Righteouſneſs are brought to light by the working of the Holy Ghoſt, who worketh the will and deed of his good pleaſure; and with the ſame good will and pleaſure it is brought forth, without bondage or conſtraint.</p>
               <p>And in whom the bonds of iniquity are broken, the world end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and all things become new, and all things of God, there dwells not ſelf-righteouſneſs, nor ſpirit of bondage; but that is the new creature which is in <hi>Chriſt Jeſus</hi> created unto good works, and not in ſelf; and the Heavens new, and the Earth new, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in dwells Righteouſneſs, as it is in Chriſt Jeſus revealed from God in Spirit and Power without the Law manifeſt, to which the Law and the Prophets bear witneſs, having foretold what glory and freedom ſhould be revealed in the latter dayes at the Seeds appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; and the Letter teſtifies of this life and power, but is not this life, but the Spirit gives this life and freedom, that it may be of grace freely, and the glory of the Lord, who is that Spirit; and here is the boaſter and ſelf excluded, and all fruitleſs trees con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned, and ſeen to come ſhort of the glory of God, of whoſe works he is not either root or off-ſpring.</p>
               <p>And before you can judge of this Freedom, or the nature of the works that ſpring thereof, or inherit the power that brings forth this Righteouſneſs, you muſt own the Judgment of Him that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demns the man of ſin in you, and receive him for your Law-giver which will break you off from the world, and would have you to deny the forms and images, and bring you from under its power; that's he that breaks the houſe of bondage, and ſets the righteous Seed at liberty, to bear the fruits which are of God. And thus hath Chriſt ſent his ſervants to ſeek the loſt, and to gather them from among bryers and thorns, and bring them to <hi>Zion</hi> one by one; and as they were gained out of ſin, ſo the Devils kingdom fell and grew weaker by every ſervant he loſt, and Chriſts Kingdom increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, until the Kingdoms of this world become the Kingdom of Righteouſneſſe, wherein the righteous King reigns; And out of cruel mockings, ſcorning, and bloody perſecutions, they gathered the loſt, and gained them to God, yea ſometimes pulled them out
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:62428:19"/>
of the fire, ſuch hath been their faith and zeal for Chriſt, and his holy Kingdom, and their ſtedfaſtneſs to that work to which they were called and hired; and the furie of the adverſary, and his oppoſite power againſt him in his ſervants hath often reached unto blood, rendering evil for love to their ſouls.</p>
               <p>Wherefore take heed to your ſelves you that name the Lord and call him Maſter; depart from iniquity, and obey the good; This is his work; if you be his ſervants, he hath called you to holineſſe as he is holy; And that you turn from the world, and repent of his works who is the prince of it, and deny him and them openly, and in ſecret; if you will ſerve the holy One, you muſt bear his mark, and open your heart to him, and your mouth for him, as confidently as the ſervants of ſin do for it, that your Light might ſhine againſt the darkneſſe of this world in the face of the perverſe and crooked generation; that it may appear to all men that the wayes of the Lord, and the world are not one, nor their ſervants one, nor their words one, nor their garments one, nor their table one; in all things bearing his Image and Glory above his Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary, that it may appear whoſe Family you belong to, and what is his Glory who hath hired you, and what is the Work of your Lord in the World.</p>
               <p>And herein may all people, as in a glaſs, ſee your ſelves and what you are to God in this his day, and what againſt him; theſe are the two maſters which Chriſt tells of, which none can ſerve, but the one he hates who ſerves the other; ſo now, who hath hired you? whom do you ſerve? and whom do you hate? Is it the World you ſerve? then you hate Chriſt; Is it Chriſt? then you deny the World: And theſe are plain things, and you may read as you go, if you will, whoſe buſineſs you go about, and whoſe hand you ſtrengthen. If you commit ſin and plead for it, then you war againſt him that is manifeſt to deſtroy ſin: And if you ſay, ſin muſt live in you while you live, then while you live the Devil muſt have a place and power in you, and a kingdom as long as you live; and if you believe to overcome ſin, then you wait for the Kingdom of God, which conſiſts in Righteouſneſs, and believe to ſee it, and ſeek it daily with your whole heart; for it is not words which take the Kingdom, but power of Faith againſt the evil one.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="38" facs="tcp:62428:20"/>Neither is it forms and profeſſions, or any outward thing that can vanquiſh the Devil; for he is a ſpirit, and by a ſpiritual power muſt he be reſiſted; and the weapons muſt be ſpiritual and mighty through God, which caſts down his ſeat in man: though many are led out from form to form, and deny that power of God in them, and obey the power of ſin in them; not knowing that power which layes the Ax to the root of the evil tree, out of which all the evil ſprings; and theſe are manifeſt to be ſuch as are not hired: what ever your forms may be, which you chuſe and change, you are but in the market-place at the beſt, not yet come into the Vineyard of God, till you be ſet on work againſt ſin, to pluck up, and cut down every evil thing that offends in the Kingdom of God, with his ſpiritual Light and Power; which Kingdom is within you; and that which offends is within you, and that which is offended is within, and that which is loſt and fallen is within, and there to be ſought; and the Pearl, and the Seed, and the Word, and the Law of the Spirit of Life, and the Covenant is within; and this is not ſeen nor believed, nor can it ſhine till the Houſe of God be ſwept, and the fruit of darkneſs denyed, and the Light of Chriſt turned to, and the Juſt obeyed, which gives to ſee the unjuſt and power againſt him, when the ground of darkneſs is removed by the working of Faith.</p>
               <p>And as many as be called to this work, and entred into it in truth and faith, muſt not be idle, but obey the Spirit of Life; till the houſe be cleanſed, and the unclean wrought out, and the pure exalted, and then is the reſt holy; and then you will find your reſt within you, and your God near you, and your ſouls to dwell at eaſe with God in your own habitation, whoſe Temples you are, if this you obtain by faith in him that calleth and quickeneth you to Holineſs; and the fruit is the Lords, and ſo is the Seed, and the ſafety for ever, to all, and in all that abide therein.</p>
               <p>And this is not ſelf-works, nor ſelf-will, but pure faith and obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to the Seed of God, which in you wars againſt the world, and every ſelfiſh fleſhly luſt and delight, which is the Seed of the holy Covenant, which Seed is Chriſt, the holy and juſt One, if you can receive it. This is he that makes clean and keeps you ſo, as many as obey and walk in him, and from his Spirit receives your Law, which Spirit giveth you his life to inherit here on earth;
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:62428:20"/>
if you walk in the Spirit, you ſhall not live to the fleſh. And in this life and knowledge truly learned, is anſwered that common objection which the ſpirit of the world makes againſt the holy Life and Kingdom, ſaying, If it were poſſible that we could live with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſin, then we need no Saviour, yea the ſame that cleanſes the houſe muſt keep it ſo; and he that's the death of ſin, is the life of righteouſneſs, and the ſame light and fear of God which leads to the putting off the old man with his affections and evil works, leads to put on the new man which is Chriſt, and ſo to walk in him, which is renewed after the image of him that created him, where Chriſt is all in life and guiding; and the good man keeps the houſe, not the ſtrong man; and how can that man ſay he needs no Saviour, who can do nought without him, whoſe righteous life is both food and rayment, and his light their armor daily, againſt the evil in this world in every thought, word and work? and in whom this is not ſo, Chriſt is not all; and in whom it is ſo, they are compleat in him, and do not ſay they have no need of him, but conſeſs him in them their head and glory; and this is the Kingdom of God up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on earth, and the King in his Kingdom, which you that reſiſt in your faith and practice, deny the Lord, and his Power, and his Faith, and his Prayer, which is, <hi>Thy Kingdom come, thy will be done on Earth as it is in Heaven;</hi> where no ſin is.</p>
               <p>And this further, to all you that in words profeſſe Jeſus Chriſt to be your Lord and Maſter, let it be in Truth and Righteouſneſſe, that you may have his witneſſe thereto, who is pure and clean and cannot join to evil, but is an open witneſſe againſt every appearance of it; and ſo are all his Servants, whom he hath hired and ſent into the world; in what place or imployment ſo ever you are in, if you be his ſervants, you are chiefly about his work, and not your own. Now his work is manifeſt in every appearance of his in this world; it is againſt ſin, and to deſtroy the works of the Devil out of this world, mind this; To deſtroy the works of the Devil out of this world, that ſo the Kingdoms of this world may become the Kingdoms of Chriſt Jeſus, and the moſt Holy One may rule and bring forth fruits therein. Now his Servants are known by this, that they ſtand for the Kingdom of Chriſt in this world, and his works, and againſt all the works of the Devil in this world, to deſtroy and bring down, and make an end of ſin in this world;
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:62428:21"/>
and the ſervants of the Devil are known in the contrary, by being in his work, which is to keep ſin in this world while people live, and this is the ſtrength of his kingdom; take away ſin, and take away his kingdom here, and his power here, and his place here; for where he is reſiſted he flies, but where he is received he ſets up his throne, and takes pleaſure in his ſervants, and they in his works; which is to encreaſe deceit and vanity in them, and to fill their hearts with every luſt; and ſo ſtrongly carrying out their hearts thereunto, that they have no delight in that which is contrary, nor can believe that ever any can receive power in the Spirit of Chriſt againſt him, or ſuch redemption as to overcome him, and be freed from him in all his works in this world: And here is an agreement with death in your faith, and a covenant confeſſed with unrighteouſneſs.</p>
               <p>And you that are in this mind and belief, you are not hired of Chriſt Jeſus the Righteous, nor have you received his Faith, which is pure, as he is pure; and believes unto Righteouſneſs, and unto Victory, and not unto ſin; and that's his faith, which overcomes the world, and the prince of it, and reſiſts him ſtedfaſt in the faith, in hope of victory in the end; and this faith his ſervants confeſs openly, which faith the world cannot receive, but confeſs the contrary openly; and ſo you are kept captive at his will, and you believe you muſt be his ſervants while you live here in this world; And this faith you confeſs openly againſt the victory of Chriſt; and herein you are faithful to your own Maſter whoſe works you do, and plead for, and confeſs his faith, which none of the Servants of Chriſt ever confeſſed ſuch a faith, that they muſt needs ſerve ſin as long as they live; for the youngeſt and the weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt ſervant of Jeſus Chriſt, that know themſelves hired of him, they know his work is to deſtroy ſin out of the world, and to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>due the Devil, and to this work they are ſet in themſelves, by faith and power, which is in Chriſt Jeſus the Lord, and they labour in hope, having their hearts turned in them, and their faces ſet to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards holineſs, and from the world, and are ſet on their way out of the world, which is Chriſt the life that's holy, and light that's pure; and to this the mind is kept in all their travels and tribula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and temptions, which worketh in them by faith in Chriſt, more hope, and more ſtrength daily; and every thing that happens them in the way, gives experience and renewed ſtrength againſt
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:62428:21"/>
their adverſarie the Devil, while they keep cloſe to Chriſt in faith and love; and though they feel the Devil in the ſenſual part to be ſtrong and powerful, and paſt their ſtrength at preſent, yet they yeeld him not the Kingdom for that, but into the faith and hope and patience of Chriſt Jeſus they ſink down, waiting for the reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of that Life which never ſinned, but died when ſin took his kingdome, and there wait for the appearance of Chriſt with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſin to ſave them from that power of death which wars in their own members, to bring forth ſin in this world: and this is to be true in their ſervice and faithful, who wait for the Kingdom of God within them, and Righteouſneſſe thereof, and the comming of their Lord, with their minds girt up with holineſſe, and hearts ſted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſt, not to conſent to the leaſt work of the Devil, if it would gain the whole world in the aperition of the ſenſual reaſon and wiſdom.</p>
               <p>And if theſe be overtaken with a fault, it is not willingly, but as Servants of Chriſt they ſtand againſt it to the utmoſt they then ſee; and ſin being a work of the wrong maſter, they abhor it and them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves for it, and deny it, and will not plead for it, or ſeek to hide it in them, but confeſſe it, and cannot have peace till it be cleanſed out; and theſe are the little children who have an Advo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate with the Father, to whom ſin is as death, and dare not ſpeak a word for it, but againſt it in themſelves and in others, and theſe appear againſt ſin openly, and confeſs to him that is holy, with all their hearts and words.</p>
               <p>But what a difference is there betwixt one of theſe, who when they either ſee it or are told of their offence againſt the Lord, are broken before the leaſt reproof, into tears or ſorrow, condemn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing themſelves for it, and it in themſelves, openly; and you who when you are reproved for ſin, which is both open and known, you ſet your ſelves with all your ſtrength and wiſdom to plead for it, and like the Devil, bring the letter to ſtrengthen your ſelves againſt juſt reproof, and with hearts full of envie, and mouths full of reproach, you ſtand up, ſeeking to enſuare them that reprove you, in love to Chriſts Kingdom, and your ſouls, and to recover you out of the works of Satan, that his kingdom might fall in you, and ſo he have fewer ſubjects left in his power; and you be added unto the Kingdom of Chriſt, by being brought under his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, through denying your old matter, and confeſſing and
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:62428:22"/>
condemning his evil works: for a denying of the Devil and his works there muſt be ere Chriſt will receive you.</p>
               <p>And thus it is that Chriſt hath ever taken his Kingdom out of the hand of his adverſary in the world, by ſending his Servants into the high-wayes and hedges to gather his creatures out of the Devils works, by true reproof, and teſtifying againſt them where ever he led them, for which they were torn and ſcratched, and evil entreated by that evil ſpirit in whom it had power, as you now do, who riſe up againſt reproof.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Chriſt Jeſus known to be King in his Temples, through the power of the Holy Ghoſt, and ſword of the Spirit lifted up againſt the man of ſin in true Judgement.</head>
               <p>You who look for the Kingdom of Chriſt Jeſus, it ſtands not in obſervations, words and forms, but in the power of the holy Ghoſt, in judgment, in truth and righteouſneſs; If you would know his appearance to ſalvation, wait for it without ſin, in that Spirit and Power which is holy, to judge and condemn ſin; this is his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom with men if you can receive it, that he be known in his ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual power in the bodies of holy men and women, to dwell and walk in a holy life, a witneſs againſt all ſin by the breath of his mouth and Sword of his Spirit; and therein that he hath power and conſent to judge all contrary ſpirits within and without, and all contrary actions; And what ever oppoſes him in this his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom is Antichriſt, which denies Chriſt in his Temples and Houſe, whoſe Houſe and Temple is the new Creation of holy men and wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, and in whom he ſpeaks, dwells and walks, as ſaith the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures; in whom he judges the Prince of this world, and all his out-goings in the children of darkneſs, and in his own Temples ſhews forth his nature and virtue a witneſs againſt him and all his works; and he that would let this, is Antichriſt, who ſits in the Temple of Chriſt to reſiſt the Holy One, and cannot receive the Judgements of Chriſt againſt ſin in his Temples, nor his witneſs againſt ſin to Salvation, but cries, do not judge, when Truth ſpeaks, and the Spirit of Chriſt teſtifies againſt ſin in true Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; and this is he that lets and withſtands the coming of Chriſt without ſin, who withſtands him in his Temple, and denies his
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:62428:22"/>
righteous Judgement againſt ſin, and blaſphemes, and ſayes it is not he; nor is he now on earth, nor ſpeaks in any body now againſt ſin, but ſaith, <hi>Thou muſt not judge, leſt thou be judged;</hi> and ſo through deceit would turn Chriſts words againſt his work, who ſaith, <hi>I will redeem Zion with Judgement;</hi> and Chriſt did not ſpeak thoſe words to ſave ſin from Judgement, when he ſaith, <hi>Judge not, that ye be not judged,</hi> not to ſtop the mouth of Truth and Righteouſneſs; for then had he contradicted himſelf, who in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther place commands them to judge righteous Judgement? And he is manifeſt to deſtroy ſin, and not to ſave ſin, in whomſoever he is manifeſt; and for this end he liveth in his people, which Antichriſt would make as though he lived not, nor heard or ſpoke, but as a dumb Idol would he make the living God, for people to talk on, or ſet up a form of him, to make void his preſent life and ſpiritual power in his people, that he ſhould not ſhew forth his vertue, and give forth his Laws and Judgements by the mouth of his Servants, againſt the works of his adverſary where ever they appear in his eye.</p>
               <p>Therefore you profeſſors of Chriſt in words and forms, ſeek his Kingdom in you, and take heed that your forms withſtand not his powerful appearance in ſpirit; His Kingly Authority ſtands in his heavenly holy Nature and Vertue in Spirit, and not in periſhing rudiments and ſhadows without. Read in Scriptures how often Antichriſt hath deceived people, by turning theſe outward forms, to let the ſpiritual power, and ſo have kept people in words with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out life, oppoſing Chriſt in his Kingdom: So in the firſt place mind to know his ſpiritual Nature and Vertue, and what hath pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er againſt ſin, in word and in deed; therein is his Kingdom, and there is his Glory, and there he reigns. So take heed how you let that Spirit, which goeth out againſt ſin in judgment and in victory, in the leaſt of his people; and this know, that his Kingdom is ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual and within, and holy, and there are his Teſtimonies, Laws and Judgements, which he ſends out by the mouths of his Servants as he ſees fit; and its againſt the works of the evil one he teſtifies in judgement and vertue, for that is his Nature, and to that end he appears on earth to deſtroy the Devil and his works, through the Sword of his Spirit; and none will let this but Antichriſt and his
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:62428:23"/>
ſervants, whoſe works are evil, and ſo would ſtop the Mouth of Truth, and Voice of Chriſt Jeſus.</p>
               <p>So you may come to know his voyce from his Temple when you hear Judgement from the Spirit of Truth paſſing againſt pride and luſt, and all the works of the fleſh, to deſtroy out of the world, this is his voyce from his Temples in which his Throne is, his holy Kingdom and Power, and that's the voyce of Antichriſt who would let this, and ſayes, <hi>thou muſt not judge when ſin is judged,</hi> and ſo with the words of Chriſt would ſave the works of the Devil from ſhame and deſtruction: And now there be many Antichriſts in this work to withſtand the Word God in his Temples, and who ſet the Letter againſt the Spirit to keep up ſin, and to ſilence the Word of the holy Ghoſt that comes out of his houſe againſt it: and here are the Children of the holy God known, and the children of this world; the one ſeeks to cut down ſin, the other to ſave it; and both profeſſe Chriſt in words, but the end of their work makes them manifeſt.</p>
               <p>And you that are talking of Chriſts appearance, where will you allow him a place to rule in, if not in the heart and chief place in man, therein to judge and govern, and ſpeak, and give out his Laws? will you allow the evil one to utter his voice openly in man, in ſwearing, lying, and curſed ſpeaking, and every evil work, and muſt Chriſt be ſilent and dumb thereat in his veſſels when he ſees it? is not this his priviledge in his redeemed ones, as the other hath his power in his captives, that in them he may judge ſin as openly, as in the other it is acted? and this is the reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable ſervice of his choſen veſſels, to give up their bodies that he may ſpeak and act, and ſhew forth his vertues and life, and power therein, againſt the ſpirit of the world, in his veſſels: and were it not for this, none of the holy men of God need to have ſuffered nor been hated, but for the words of God ſpoken by them, as Chriſt hath ſaid, <hi>It is not you that ſpeak but the Spirit of your Father that ſpeaks in you;</hi> and this is the voice which the world knows not, and ſo would ſtop it, and ſayes <hi>it is not the Lord,</hi> not know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that juſtice and judgement are the habitation of his throne in the hearts and mouths of his people. What, muſt not the Spirit of Truth in whom he lives judge deceit and falſhood where it lives? Muſt not that which is Holy judge the unclean? muſt not the
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:62428:23"/>
lowly one judge the proud? the chaſte one judge the luſt? muſt not he that is ſpiritual judge all things? muſt not Saints judge the world? What a nation would you have this to be who would root out judgement, and yet profeſs Chriſt in you? Is Chriſt in that people where there is no judgement againſt ſin? what, none to judge pride and exceſs, lying, ſwearing, and curſed ſpeaking, falſe wayes and falſe worſhips? would you have all ſin to paſs openly without reproof? Is the Land wholly become as <hi>Sodom?</hi> mind what was their words to <hi>Lot</hi> in this caſe, <hi>This one fellow came in to ſojourn, and he will needs be a Judge; whoſe righteous ſoul was vexed daily with their unclean converſation.</hi> So would you have ſin to go openly in the ſtreets without repoof and ſhame? Where is the Holy One? in whom doth he dwell, who is of purer eyes then to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold iniquity? Is Chriſt a King, is he a Judge? is he pure and clean in heart? doth he live? can he ſee ſin and be ſilent, where he hath a mouth to ſpeak by? did he ever take up his abode in people where none would allow him a habitation and a mouth to ſpeak by? Mind his walking aforetime in his Servants, and what he did and ſpoke in them, and againſt what; and is he not ſtill a God of Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment at hand againſt his adverſary, though ſuch as know not his Voice put him afar off?</p>
               <p>So you who ſay you are for Chriſt and his Kingdom, mind whoſe kingdom ſin is in, and whoſe work it is to defend it from judgment, and take Scripture to plead for it; that is he which condemns the juſt who would clear the guilty; and that is abomination to God, and withſtands his appearance; and you that yeeld your members thereto, are not for Chriſt, but againſt him in his members, who have yeelded themſelves Servants of Truth: and ſuch as you were they who ſlew the Juſt One, his Prophets and Apoſtles (in whom the Word of God ſpoke againſt ſin) and had the Scriptures, and ſerved ſin.</p>
               <p>Wherefore if you love the appearance of Chriſt Jeſus, you muſt not love ſin, but in that principle which would not ſin, feel him that ſuffers becauſe of ſin, and yet is without ſin, and againſt ſin, and if to him you come, whoſe appearance is in that which is holy, juſt, and true, and therein joyn to him, you will love that which condemns ſin, by which he is grieved &amp; oppreſſed; and then are you for Chriſt, when you can feel and ſuffer with him, by that which he
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:62428:24"/>
ſuffers; and you will then ſee that nought is it that is offended at ſin being judged, but he that is guilty thereof,</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Grace received, and Grace rejected.</head>
               <p>THE Grace of God is that which brings Salvation to man, all men being in natural darkneſs, as they are in the world without God, ſo the Grace of God is tendred to all without reſpect of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons; And that's it in every man which gives him a ſight of Truth in himſelf, which Truth God by his Grace accepts in every man, who would have all men to come to the knowledge thereof, that they might be ſaved. Now this Grace in it ſelf is one in every man, and is of God in every man, and doth not ſpare the evil, nor deny the good in any, out of reſpect either to perſon, wiſdom, ſtrength or riches which is of this world, but hath reſpect to the Truth of Spirit in all, and their obedience thereto; therein to teach and lead to Salvation, and the true Worſhip of God in Spirit, which leads to Life eternal, and to the ſtrengthening the holy Seed in man, quickening the Soul which by ſin hath ſuffered; and this it doth by condemning ſin in every motion, that it may never ariſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the holy Seed, and alſo by miniſtring comforts and promiſes, and power in ſpirit to the ſoul in the way of its ariſing above the power of the ſon of wickedneſs, ſtill miniſtring light and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding in the hidden part to the holy Seed that hates ſin, opening that eye daily through the obedience of Truth, which the god of this world hath blinded, and purifying the Soul by putting off the body of corruption, and blinding him that ſaith he ſees, but knows not the way out of ſin, miniſtring the Law upon him.</p>
               <p>And this is the miniſtration of free Grace to every Soul that receives it; and this it worketh powerfully in all that abide in it, through the Spirit of Chriſt Jeſus; and <hi>this Grace</hi> (as ſaith the Scripture) <hi>hath appeared to all men;</hi> yea, and doth daily appear in all who truly wait in Spirit for its appearance, and gives to all ſuch a ſight of Truth in themſelves, teſtifying with or againſt every mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in their hearts, according as it ſtands in the ſight of God, whether it be good or evil, whereby the Conſcience doth accuſe or excuſe, even as God ſhall judge them by Chriſt Jeſus; So that there is no cauſe in this Grace, why any are not ſaved thereby from ſin and condemnation, but being rejected of ſome, it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:62428:24"/>
their condemnation; and the ſame thing which ſaves him that receives it in faith and obedience, condemns him that rejects it in his diſobedience; And this is the Grace of God that changeth not, which appears to all men, but only reigns to Salvation through righteouſneſs, wherein it is believed to be ſufficient and obeyed, in the Truth therewith made manifeſt.</p>
               <p>So that is the Grace of God, which is of God in man, miniſtring in Spirit light to the Soul in the midſt of darkneſs, miniſtring life to that which is dead in ſin; leading that through the vail of death up to God, from whom the Grace hath appeared, and of whom it is; and the Light thereof is Judgement, and diſcerning in every one that receives it to be led with it in Judgment, and Condemnation to ſuch as turn it into laſciviouſneſs, denying the life thereof, and the truth that leads thereto, and ſo cannot be ſaved through it; but he that receives it, and joyns to it in Spirit, becomes one with it, and by his daily ſinking into it in counſel, it grows in him, and he in it, until it becomes a habitation and cover for him againſt all e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil, and ſo he becomes gracious in words and works, daily receiving Grace for Grace of his fulneſs.</p>
               <p>And he that hath received of this Grace, and is faithful therein, muſt not miniſter of it to ſtrengthen the tranſgreſſor, who loves his ſin, and ſo is under the Law, for that is to caſt the pearls to ſwine; but to ſuch as are heavy laden and weary of ſin, to encourage a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt ſin and temptations, which all that turn from the Devil muſt be ſure to meet with; and Judgement it miniſters to the wicked, that therewith he may know his condemnation with the light of Truth, in whom Grace is denied to reign, it is their condemnation, that he is come into the world, who is full of Grace and Truth, but the Kingdom of Grace is Salvation, in whom it reigns through righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs unto eternal Life, by Jeſus Chriſt the Lord.</p>
               <p>So he that receives the teaching of Grace, comes therein to the leading of the Spirit, and ſo becomes free from ſin, is no more un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Law, but under Grace; but the Law hath power over him that walks after the fleſh, and every appearance of Grace is witneſs againſt him, by declaring him to be under the law of ſin and death, and not in Covenant with him that appears againſt ſin in the power of Grace and Truth, which is Chriſt Jeſus the Lord.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
